Hello everyone and welcome to English Pot.
My name is Marco.
My name is Catherine and a
very Merry Christmas to everyone.
That's right, Merry
Christmas. We are at that
time again where we
are celebrating Christmas.
We're having dinner with family
and friends. We're giving presents.
And of course, there
are some other traditions
that come in to play, like
for example Santa Claus.
Santa Claus, so we've got a very special
advanced level lesson for you today.
We've got a poem. It's
a very traditional poem
that is read or listened
to on the holiday.
And we're going to talk a
little bit about some of the
interesting words and
phrases that are used in this.
But first off, let's just
listen to the poem itself.
It was the night before
Christmas when all through the
house, not a creature was
stirring, not even a mouse.
The stockings were hung
by the chimney with care,
in hopes that Saint
Nicholas soon would be there.
The children were nestled,
all snug in their beds,
while visions of sugar
plums danced in their heads,
and mama in her
kerchief and eye in my cap
had just settled down
for a long winter's nap.
When out on the lawn,
there arose such a clatter,
I sprang from the bed to
see what was the matter.
A way to the window,
I flew like a flash,
tore open the shutters
and threw open a sash.
The moon on the breast
of the new fallen snow
gave the luster of
midday to objects below.
When what to my
wondering eyes should appear,
but a miniature sleigh,
an eight tiny reindeer.
With a little old driver,
so lively and quick,
I knew in a moment
it must be Saint Nick.
More rapid than eagles,
his coarser's day came, and
he whistled and shouted
and caught them by name.
Now dasher, now dancer,
now prancer and vixen,
on comet, on cupid,
on donder and blitzen.
To the top of the
porch, to the top of the
wall, now dash away,
dash away, dash away all.
As dry leaves that before
the wild herd canes fly,
when they meet with an
obstacle mount to the sky.
So up to the housetop,
the coarser's day flew with
the sleigh's full of toys,
and Saint Nicholas too.
And then, in a twinkling,
I heard on the roof,
the prancing and
pawing of each little hoof.
As I drew in my head and
was turning around, down
the chimney, Saint
Nicholas came with a bound.
He was dressed on fur
from his head to his toe, and
his clothes were all
tarnished with ashes and soot.
A bundle of toys, he
had flung on his back, and
he looked like a peddler
just opening his pack.
His eyes, how they twinkled,
his dimples, how merry.
His cheeks were like
roses, his nose like a cherry.
His draw little mouth was
drawn up in a bow, and
the beard of his chin
was as white as the snow.
The stump of a pipe,
he held tight in his teeth,
and the smoke, and
encircled his head like a wreath.
He had a broad face in
the little round belly that
shook when he laughed
like a bowl full of jelly.
He was chubby and
plump, a rattle jelly elf, and
I laughed when I saw
him, in spite of myself.
A wink of his eye,
and a twist of his head,
soon gave me to know
I had nothing to dread.
He spoke not a word, but
when straight to work, and
filled all the stockings,
then turned with a jerk.
And laying his finger aside of his nose
and giving a nod up the chimney he rose.
He sprang to his sleigh,
so his team gave a whistle,
and the way they all flew
like a down of a thistle.
But I heard him exclaim,
air as he drove out of sight.
Happy Christmas to all,
and to all, a good night!
Alright, we're back, so
the poem is very nice, it's
long, and just to recap what
the poem is talking about.
What is the general story of the poem?
The story of the poem is that Santa
Claus is coming to visit someone's house.
And there's a person in the story
who is watching Santa Claus arrive.
And he's seeing Santa Claus take the
reindeer up onto the roof, come down the
chimney, and lay the presents out for the
children, filling the stockings as well.
Okay, so it's basically a nice poetic
description of Santa Claus, and also
it goes into describe in a very nice
way the way Santa Claus looks like.
It's very descriptive, we have
descriptions of what Santa Claus
looks like, what he's wearing
his smile, how he's a little bit fat.
We also have descriptions
of the animals, these special
animals that we hear about
so often that are called reindeer.
Alright, so we've divided up
the poem into by line, so then it's
going to be easier for you to go
to the line that we're talking about.
Let's start with the
first line, with this
first word that's
actually very interesting.
It was the night before Christmas
when all through the house.
So what does this
first word mean?
It was an abbreviation, so
it's shortened version of it was.
Okay, so, but do you actually use
this now in like if you're writing?
No, this is not something
I would use now in
writing, and it's not
something I would say.
It's actually more of an
archaic form, something
that you might hear in
poetry or historical writing.
Okay, so it was the night
before Christmas, right?
So we're talking
about December 24th.
The night of December 24th, that's right.
Alright, so the first two lines talk
about how it was the night before
Christmas and in the house there
was nothing stirring, not even a mouse.
So not even the smallest
little animal, so it's
very quiet in the house
is what's happening.
So now we jump to line
number seven where the poet
describes and mama in
her kerchief and I in my cap.
So we know that the
person talking is the dad,
because he's talking about
himself and mama, mother.
They're in bed together, and
mama in her kerchief and I in my
cap, so I'm wearing a night cap,
a cover on my head, like a hat.
And mama has a kerchief.
Oh, a kerchief is another
abbreviation, it's short for handkerchief.
And a handkerchief is a
piece of fabric or cloth that
sometimes we use for our noses
when we have to blow our nose.
But also you can use a kerchief
in your hair to cover your hair.
So if you can imagine it, this must take
place, I don't know, maybe 50, 60 years
ago when dads used to wear hats to bed
and women also handkerchiefs on their hair.
Or longer, maybe 200 years ago when people
wore these long night hats and red caps.
The pajamas and everything.
All right, now let's jump
over to line 18 and 19 when
he's talking about the
reindeer and the sleigh arriving.
He says, "I knew in a
moment it must be Saint Nick.
" This is another way of
calling Santa Claus, right?
Saint Nicholas is his name, but
you also call him claws or Santa Claus.
Okay.
And then he said, "More rapid
than eagles his courseers they came.
" So the word order is a bit strange
here, this is common in poetry.
We could also say his courseers
came more rapidly than eagles.
They were very, very fast.
But what are these courseers?
We're talking about the
animals pulling Santa Claus.
And what are those animals again?
They're called reindeer.
Reindeer.
So the reindeer are very, very fast.
Okay, that's right because
he's making the comparison
about how fast eagles
are compared to them.
Okay.
And we hear their names, right?
Exactly.
He goes on to say, "Now
dasher, now dancer, now prancer.
" And all of their names, Vixen,
Comet, Cupid, Donder, and Blitzen.
All eight reindeer, each
animal has its own name.
That's right.
So all eight reindeer,
actually we're missing
one though, that's
very common nowadays.
The reindeer that goes in the
front lighting, illuminating the sky.
Rudolph, the red nose reindeer.
You might know the song,
That's right.
So there are actually nine
reindeer nowadays, but
I guess the story was before
the Rudolph story came out.
All right.
So those are, this is interesting because
those are the names of all the reindeer.
I'm not sure which order they are, I don't
know who's in the back was in the front.
Yeah, I don't know either.
But it's important to
know that they're very
fast and they come
down and then they go up.
They have to take Saint Nicholas to the
roof of the house, on top of the house.
That's right.
So now he arrives to the top of the house.
Line 32, we see, down the chimney,
Saint Nicholas came with a bound.
He came quickly down the chimney, boom.
And at the end, he's all dressed
in fur from his head to his foot.
So top to bottom, he has fur on.
That's right.
And I think he's got fur because
he lives in the North Pole, right?
That's right.
It's very cold where Santa Claus lives.
So he has to wear these
clothes that are very warm.
Okay.
And obviously, since he is going up
and down chimneys in line 34, we see.
And his clothes were
tarnished with ashes and soot.
So to tarnish or tarnish means dirty.
Something is tarnished if it's dirty.
So his clothes were
dirty with ashes and soot.
This means that, you
know, in your fireplace when
the fire is gone, there's
some gray and black stuff.
And that's what's on Santa Claus' clothes.
Okay.
Very good.
So, and then we go on to line 35, a
bundle of toys he had flung on his back.
And he looked like a
peddler just opening his pack.
All right, a peddler.
Now, this is not just
something we talk about.
On Christmas, you know, we
have peddlers all year round.
What are peddlers?
What do they do?
Basically, they go around selling things.
So maybe you see them in
a small market or sometimes
in different places and
maybe not on the streets.
You see them selling little things like
toys or combs or books, something like that.
Oranges, you see fruit
peddlers, people who sell fruit.
Or you can see those watch
peddlers, you know, they say,
"Would you like a Rolex watch peddler?"
So that's what they do, right?
They're informal salesman.
They don't have a store.
They work on the street.
So this is why Santa looks like a peddler.
He isn't in a store.
He has a bag and he
says, "Look in my bag.
" Right, exactly.
Now, from line 37, we go on to
describe the way Santa Claus looks like.
So he says his eyes how they
twinkled, his dimples how merry.
Dimples are those small
circles on your cheeks.
So some people, when they smile,
they have these small holes or circles.
Those are dimples.
They're very cute.
That's right.
So not everyone has them, right?
Some people, when they
smile, you can see those dimples.
All right.
So, and his cheeks were like
roses, his nose like a cherry.
So that's, we're saying that they're red.
They're red, they're pink.
Okay.
Now, in line 39 he says, his draw
little mouth was drawn up like a bow.
Now, draw is a word
that some people still use.
It's pretty common in places like England.
We don't use it as much in America.
We say funny instead.
But something that is drawl,
D-R-O-L-L, drawl is funny.
Okay.
So his mouth, his face is funny looking.
His face is funny looking.
All right.
And going on to line 45, we're
describing how he was chubby and plump.
So we're basically saying
he was a little bit fat.
Yes.
And a right, a right, jolly old elf.
So what is an elf?
An elf is actually normally
we talk about elves.
So one elf, two elves, as people,
little people who help Santa.
They're mythical creatures who live in
the North Pole and who make presents.
So an elf is a small creature
who makes presents.
Okay.
Or maybe lives in the woods.
There are many
different stories with elves.
Elves, right.
Right.
And in 1946, we say, and I laughed
when I saw him in spite of myself.
What does he mean by in spite of myself?
And this is really important.
And this is something we say in
English all the time in spite of myself.
So I laughed in spite of myself.
So I didn't want to laugh.
I wanted to be serious.
But I did laugh.
So in spite of myself,
I didn't want to laugh.
I laughed anyway.
So you say in spite of myself when
you did the thing you did not want to do.
Okay.
And finishing off, we are going
towards the last three lines where we say,
and a way they all flew
like the down of a thistle.
What is a thistle?
They're talking about the
part of a flower that's a thistle.
Okay.
So they all flew away like
quickly, rapidly like the little flower.
Well, you know, when a flower is
sending its seeds out, it's down its white.
So maybe if you blow on a flower
with the white seeds, they blow away.
That's what it looks like.
It looks like the seeds of
a flower being blown away.
Very easy.
Okay.
Like 55 says, but I heard him exclaim air.
He drove out of sight.
So this is an older way of
saying as he drove out of sight.
So as he's flying away, I
can't see him anymore.
Almost I can't see him anymore.
He exclaimed something.
So air means, you know,
while while this is happening.
Now this is another one of those maybe old
English words that we don't use anymore.
Right?
You wouldn't really use air.
Air I was walking to school, I saw.
Right.
The milk man.
No.
We don't say this
anymore, but you will find it
in poetry and you might
also find it in stories.
Okay.
And line 56, he ends.
And this is very the
famous way that this
poem ends by saying have be
Christmas to all and to all a good night.
Happy Christmas to all
and to all a good night.
Yeah, this is the, and the first line
of the poem are the most famous.
Everyone knows these.
Okay.
Very good.
So a beautiful poem.
Why don't we listen to it one more time.
It was the night before
Christmas when all
through the house, not a creature
was stirring, not even a mouse.
The stockings were
hung by the chimney with
care in hopes that Saint
Nicholas soon would be there.
The children were
nestled, all snug in their
beds, while visions
of sugar plums danced
in their heads, and mawah
in her kerchief and eye in
my cap had just settled
down for a long winter's nap.
When out on the lawn,
there arose such a clatter.
I sprang from the bed to
see what was the matter.
Away to the window,
I flew like a flash, tore
open the shutters and
threw open the sash.
The moon on the breast
of the new fallen snow
gave the luster of
midday to objects below.
When what to my
wondering eyes should appear
but a miniature sleigh,
an eight tiny reindeer.
With a little old driver
so lively and quick,
I knew in a moment
it must be Saint Nick.
More rapid than eagles,
his coarsers they came and
he whistled and shouted
and called them by name.
Mount Dasher, now dancer,
now prancer and vixen.
On comet, on cupid, on donder and blitzen.
To the top of the porch,
to the top of the wall.
Now dash away, dash away, dash away all.
As dry leaves that
before the wild hurricanes
fly, when they meet with
an obstacle mount to the sky.
So, up to the house top, the coarsers
they flew with the sleigh's full of toys.
And Saint Nicholas too.
And then, in a twinkling,
I heard on the roof,
the prancing and
pawing of each little hoof.
As I drew in my head and
was turning around, down
the chimney, Saint
Nicholas came with a bound.
He was dressed on fur
from his head to his toe and
his clothes were all
tarnished with ashes and soot.
A bundle of toys, he
had flung on his back and
he looked like a peddler
just opening his pack.
His eyes, how they twinkled,
his dimples, how merry.
His cheeks were like
roses, his nose like a cherry.
His draw little mouth
was drawn up in a bow and
the beard of his chin
was as white as the snow.
The stump of a pipe,
he held tight in his teeth
and the smoke and encircled
his head like a wreath.
He had a broad face in
the little round belly that
shook when he laughed
like a bowl full of jelly.
He was chubby and
plump, a rattle jelly elf, and
I laughed when I saw
him, in spite of myself.
A wink of his eye
and a twist of his head
soon gave me to know
I had nothing to dread.
He spoke not a word but
went straight to work and
filled all the stockings
then turned with a jerk.
And laying his finger aside of his nose
and giving a nod up the chimney he rose.
He sprang to his sleigh
to his team gave a whistle
and the way they all flew
like the down of a thistle.
But I heard an exclaim
air as he drove out of sight.
Happy Christmas to all
and to all a good night!
Alright, so this is one of
the very famous poems
you can listen to or read
about it during Christmas.
That's right, it's a classic,
it's something that you
think about people listening
to in front of the fireplace.
And they're drinking their egg nog
and talking about how wonderful family is.
And so yeah, it's a
classic, it's something
that we often talk about
and read and listen to.
Alright, so it's very
interesting because it's
part of the American
tradition of Christmas.
I think maybe also in
other parts of the world the
poem might be translated
or also might be popular.
But you know Santa Claus and all
these things are traditions that are
observed in some countries and it's
very interesting to understand them.
Absolutely, and I'm very curious to
know about your Christmas traditions.
What do you do in your home country
on Christmas Eve or on Christmas Day?
Do you know any poems like this or
do you listen to this poem in translation?
Let us know our website is EnglishPod.com.
Alright guys, we'll see you there and have
a Merry Christmas! Merry Christmas! Bye!